Okay, thank you.
好的，谢谢。
Okay, so good afternoon, good evening, good morning, good night, wherever you are,
好的，下午好，傍晚好，早上好，晚上好，无论你在哪里，
we're going to talk today about transactions.
今天我们要谈的是事务。
And you probably noticed,
你们可能注意到了，
the reading material for today a little bit more tutorial in nature,
今天的阅读材料本质上更多是教程，
we're not studying a particular system,
我们不是在研究一个特定的系统，
and see how a set of ideas are implemented in that system,
看看一系列的想法是如何在这个系统中实现的，
instead what we're gonna be doing is talking about just the concept of transactions,
相反，我们要做的只是谈论事务的概念，
because it it shows up in the next two papers,
因为它会出现在接下来的两个论文中，
that we'll be studying those two papers,
我们将研究这两篇论文，
have a quite a lot of material in them,
其中有相当多的材料，
and assume familiar with transactions,
假设对事务很熟悉，
in particular that you're familiar with the two core ideas that we'll see the today's lecture,
特别是你们熟悉我们今天课程中的两个核心思想，
namely 2-phase locking and 2-phase commit,
也就是两阶段锁和两阶段提交，
and sometimes they are abbreviated as you know 2PC for 2-phase commit
有时，它们被缩写， 2PC 表示两阶段提交，
and 2PL for 2-phase locking,
2PL 表示两阶段锁，
one point of confusion,
有一点令人困惑，
the two terms really don't have to do much,
这两个术语不需要做太多事情，
don't have to, don't do,
不需要，
really not much related,
没有什么关系，
you know they happen to have both words two words 2-phase in it,
他们碰巧有两个词 2-phase ，
but you know they show completely different problems,
但是，它们表现完全不同的问题，
they they have to also show up on typically in the context of transactions,
它们还出现在事务的背景下，
but there are even outside of transactions,
但是即使在事务之外，
they are good ideas or worthwhile ideas,
它们也是好想法或有价值的想法，
and so don't let your self confused by the fact that they both have 2-phase in it,
所以不要让你自己被他们都有 2-phase 所迷惑，
they're pretty unrelated.
它们没什么关系。
Okay, so I'm just gonna dive in a little bit
好的，所以我要稍微深入一点，
and start talking about transactions in general,
开始谈论一般的事务，
and the reason that we're going to care about transactions a lot is,
我们非常关注事务的原因是，
that we want to be able to do cross-machine operations.
我们希望能够进行跨机器操作。
So the problem that we're going to try to tackle
所以我们尝试解决的问题，
in this lecture as well as in the two upcoming papers
在这个课程以及即将看到的两篇论文中，
is cross-machine atomic ops.
是跨机器的原子操作。
And so for example just to make it a little bit concrete,
举个例子，让它变得更具体，
let's say we have a client,
假设我们有一个客户端，
we have two,
我们有两个，
we have a sharded key value server,
我们有一个分片的键值服务器，
so some of the keys are on key value server 1,
所以一些键在键值服务器 1 上，
some are on key value server 2,
一些在键值服务器 2 上，
so the keys are split across them,
所以键分布在它们上面，
so for example, maybe kv1 has x, kv2 has y,
例如， kv1 有 x ， kv2 有 y ，
and we want to basically want to atomic operation across those two keys,
我们想要跨这两个键进行原子操作，
and the easy way or the classic example in the context of transactions
在事务的背景下，简单的方法或经典的例子
is always doing a transfer.
总是进行转账。
So let's say the client wants to do a transfer from x to y,
假设客户端想要进行从 x 到 y 的转账，
here's our client,
这是我们的客户端，
and it's gonna do basically put you know to x,
它会对 x 做一次 put ，
to maybe add or subtract from the account,
从帐户中增加或减少，
so let's do x,-1
所以我们做 x,-1 ，
and then the client is going to do put of y,+1,
然后客户端要做 put(y,+1) ，
transfer namely one dollar from you know the account x to the account y.
从账户 x 向账户 y 转账一美元。
And our goal is basically going to be,
我们的目标是，
you know we want atomicity with respect to failures and concurrency.
我们希望在故障和并发方面保持原子性。
So even if you know [] kv,
所以，即使第一个 kv ，
the first key value server fails after the put,
第一个键值服务器在 put 之后失败，
then we want like to arrange it,
那么我们想要安排，
basically the transfer didn't happen at all,
转账根本不会发生，
so generally the semantics that we're looking for is that,
所以，我们要寻找的语义是，
both operations happen or neither one of them happens.
这两种操作都会发生或者都不会发生。
And so, similarly from concurrency perspective,
所以，从并发性的角度来看，
if another client is running
如果另一个客户端正在运行，
and also tries to inspect these accounts,
并且尝试检查这些帐户，
now what we would like to be the case is that,
现在我们想要的是
both puts show atomically,
这两个 put 原子地显示，
and so other transaction cannot observe intermediate results,
所以其他事务不能观察到中间结果，
where intermediate result,
中间结果，
for example, the money is deducted from x,
比如，钱从 x 中减去，
that hasn't been added to y yet.
没有加到 y 上。
So, these are the type of things we want to do
所以，这些就是我们想要做的事情，
and it's complete common in distributed systems,
这在分布式系统中非常常见，
you know that you would like to do operation across shards.
比如你希望跨分片执行操作。
So that's sort of the context of what we'd like to do
所以，这就是我们想要做的事情的背景，
and the general plan for doing this is comes directly from the database community,
这样做的总体方案来自数据库社区，
this general plan is transactions.
这个总体方案就是事务。
And what we'd like to do is basically group these operations,
我们想要做的是对这些操作进行分组，
for example in the case with the transfer,
例如，在转账的情况中，
two put operations into a single transaction.
两个 put 操作作为一个事务。
And, we like, then the property that this transaction executes atomically,
然后，这个事务原子地执行，
so you know typically this requires some program annotations,
这通常需要一些编程注解，
so begin_x to indicate that the client wants to start a transaction,
所以 begin_x 表示客户端想要启动事务，
you know may be then you know the operations like add, you know add x -1
然后可能是 add 操作， add(x,-1) ，
and then add y you know +1,
然后 add(y,+1) ，
and then you have to indicate when the transaction is completed
然后，你必须指明事务何时完成，
and so typically we come to make a commit.
通常我们使用 commit 。
And, and so the semantics that we're looking for is that,
所以，我们寻找的语义是，
these operations are executed atomically
这些操作原子地执行，
with respect to concurrency and respect to failure.
对于并发和故障。
And just to make it a little bit more exciting,
为了让它更激动人心，
let's look at second transaction,
让我们来看看第二个事务，
so that we can look at some case studies
我们可以看一些案例研究，
about how transactions actually interact,
关于事务如何[互动]，
we might have a second transaction begin_x,
我们可能有第二个事务 begin_x ，
which reads actually these accounts,
它读取这些账户，
so t1 gets x, and then t2 you know gets y,
所以 t1 得到 x ，然后 t2 得到 y ，
and print t1 and t2,
并打印 t1 和 t2 ，
and then end or commit.
然后结束或 commit 。
So we have a second transaction,
所以，我们有第二个事务，
that basically reads the account x and y and prints the values.
它读取帐户 x 和 y ，并打印值。
And one reason that we have two transactions,
我们有两个事务的一个原因是，
so that we can look from the concurrency perspective,
我们可以从并发性的角度来看，
how these transactions actually ordered,
这些事务是如何排序的，
what are legal outcome and what are illegal outcomes.
什么是合法结果，什么是非法结果。
Transactions turned out to be a general, almost like a piece of magic,
事务就像是一个魔法，
basically programmers can annotate these begin and end operations,
程序员可以注解这些 begin 和 end 操作，
and it takes a whole group of operations together,
它使一组操作一起，
make them atomic
使它们原子化，
and use the system will take care of everything,
使用这个系统会处理好一切，
it will take care of the locking,
它会负责锁，
will take care of the recovery,
会负责恢复，
it's all like the programmer doesn't have to worry about it,
程序员不必担心这个问题，
the transactions is a very very powerful construct,
事务是一个非常强大的结构，
and they're useful in non distributed systems,
它们在非分布式系统中很有用，
you know you have a single database machine or multi-core database machine,
你有一台单数据库机器或多核数据库机器，
and clients are submitting transactions to it,
客户端向它提交事务，
then the transaction system will execute these transactions
然后事务系统执行这些事务
as much as concurrently as possible,
尽可能并发地（执行），
but also even if machine fails, it comes back up,
但即使机器出现故障，它也会恢复正常，
you know you can actually expect the results to be there.
你可以期待结果就在那里。
And our focus of course is going to be distributed transactions,
当然，我们的重点是分布式事务，
you know what I had the previous slide,
在我之前的幻灯片里，
namely one example across shards,
也就是一个跨分片的例子，
which is a common case in data centers.
这在数据中心很常见。
The typical API of transaction also has one more operation
事务通常的 API 还有一个操作，
that I didn't list here,
我没有列在这里，
and that is abort,
也就是 abort ，
so the two transactions shown here are both committing,
这里显示的两个事务都是 commit ，
but you could immediately have transaction that decides to abort,
但是你可以直接终止事务，
you know for example you might discover that,
比如你可能会发现，
for example transaction T1 might check
例如，事务 T1 可以检查
the x has sufficient money in it in the account,
x 帐户中是否有足够的钱，
and if the account doesn't have sufficient money,
如果账户中没有足够的钱，
instead of calling commit, it would call abort,
不是调用 commit ，而是调用 abort ，
and at that point the transaction would be cancelled,
这个时候，事务将被取消，
and even if the transaction aborts you know sort of halfway through,
即使事务在一半时中止，
and maybe has done some put operations,
也许已经做了一些 put 操作，
the still the semantics should be,
语义仍然应该是，
that none of those put operations actually happened.
这些 put 操作都没有发生。
So in all cases where it's abort or commit,
所以，在所有 abort 或 commit 的情况下，
either all of them happen or none of them happen,
要么全部发生，要么一个都不发生，
never partial result,
永远不会有部分结果，
abort also might be called by the transaction system itself,
事务系统本身也可以调用 abort ，
for example as we'll see later,
例如，我们稍后将看到，
if a there's a, there's a deadlock between two transactions,
如果两个事务之间存在死锁，
then the transaction system actually can abort one of the transactions,
则事务系统可以中止其中一个事务，
in the,
在，
so that the other transaction continue
让其他事务继续，
and maybe retry later the transaction that was abort.
并且稍后重试已经中止的事务。
Okay, so this is sort of primitives,
好的，这是原语，
you know begin_x commit and abort, three key interface operations.
begin_x commit 和 abort ，三个关键接口操作。
And then the semantics of transactions
然后事务的语义
are typically summarized by a single word, namely ACID,
通常由单个词语来概括，即 ACID ，
and that stands for four key properties with transactions.
这代表了事务的四个关键属性。
One, it's atomic,
第一，它是原子的，
and here really atomic refers to the case,
这里的原子表示的情况，
where we have two transactions running,
我们有两个事务运行，
and one transaction does multiple put operations or multiple add operations,
一个事务执行多个 put 操作或多个 add 操作，
all those results will be,
所有这些结果都是，
all visible to the other transaction or none of them will be visible,
全部对另一事务可见或者全部不可见，
so that's one aspect,
所以这是一个方面，
sorry, I say this, I said this is wrong,
抱歉，我说的这个不对，
so the atomic actually means to crash recovery case,
原子性意思是崩溃恢复的情况，
so, if a transaction actually multiple put operations,
如果一个事务有多个 put 操作，
the transaction crashes halfway,
事务在中途崩溃，
the rule is that all the writes are visible,
规则是所有的写入都是可见的，
all writes around a stable storage or none of them,
所有写入都进入存储或都没有，
was the atomic sort of respect to crash recovery.
原子性与崩溃恢复有关。
The C stands for consistent,
C 代表一致性，
which is something we're mostly not going to talk about,
这是我们不太会谈论的事情，
it's more related to databases,
它更多地与数据库相关，
it's often the case that database have internal variants,
通常情况下，数据库具有内部变量，
like referential integrity, is one of them,
比如参照完整性就是其中之一，
and the transaction is supposed to maintain that consistency,
而事务应该保持这种一致性，
and so no internal consistencies,
所以没有内部一致性，
this is going to be less of a topic for us today.
对于我们今天来说，这不是一个话题。
The three is isolated, the I stands for isolated,
第三个是隔离性， I 代表隔离性，
and isolated was,
隔离性是，
what I just said earlier incorrectly,
我之前说错的，
isolated actually refers to the case,
隔离性指的是这种情况，
we're running two transactions,
我们运行两个事务，
and they don't see,
它们不会看到，
they should not observe intermediate results from each other,
它们不应该观察到彼此的中间结果，
so again all the writes are applied,
所以应用所有写入，
all or nothing with respect to [] to another transactions.
其他事务看到全部或没有。
And finally, the D stands for durable,
最后， D 代表耐久性，
meaning that if the transaction commits,
意味着如果事务提交，
then the results are written to a stable storage,
结果写入稳定存储，
so that if the system crashes, comes back up later,
如果系统崩溃，稍后又恢复，
the latest writes or the latest transactions,
最新写入或最新事务，
the latest committed transactions are actually recorded on stable storage.
最新提交的事务会记录在稳定存储上。
Any questions about quick introduction to transactions?
关于事务的简介，有什么问题吗？
Okay, so I'm gonna talk basically about two topics quite a bit,
好的，我主要会讲两个话题，
namely the A part of the transactions and the I part of transactions.
也就是事务的 A 部分和 I 部分，
We're gonna start with the I part,
我们将从 I 部分开始，
and talk a little bit about what actually correct isolation means.
稍微讨论一下隔离性是什么。
So basically what we're looking for is a definition
所以我们要找的是一个定义，
for correct execution of multiple transactions or concurrency transactions,
正确执行多个事务或并发事务，
in the typical definition or [] standard in the database literature,
在数据库文献中的典型定义或标准中，
is called serializable or serializability,
称为可串行化，
and what that means is that,
这意味着，
if you have two transactions or many transactions,
如果你有两个或多个事务，
they execute concurrently,
它们同时执行，
then the outcome has to be some serial order,
那么结果肯定是某种串行的顺序，
so either t1 executes before t2 or t2 executes before t1,
所以 t1 在 t2 之前执行，或者 t2 在 t1 之前执行，
there's some serial or serial order,
有某种串行的顺序，
and the serial order has to produce the same outcome as the concurrent execution,
串行顺序必须产生与并发执行相同的结果，
so you get run two transaction concurrently,
所以你同时运行两个事务，
they produce some outcome,
它们产生一些结果，
that outcome is only valid or legal or correct,
这个结果是有效的、合法的或正确的，
if it could have been the result of a serial execution.
这可能是串行执行的结果。
So just to make concrete, for example,
所以，为了更具体一些，
let's say in the account case x starts out as being 10,
假设在帐户中 x 从 10 开始，
y starts out as being 10,
y 从 10 开始，
we run these two transactions,
我们运行这两个事务，
that we had earlier on the board,
我们之前在白板上看到的，
here might be what the two transactions are,
这两个事务的内容，
and one basically moves one between two accounts
一个是在两个帐户之间移动一，
and the other one prints the results of the two.
另一个是打印两个的结果。
So if you think a little bit about it,
所以你稍微想一下，
if t1 goes first,
如果 t1 先执行，
then the outcome is gonna be 9,10,
那么结果将是 9,10 ，
and the print statement is going to be,
而打印语句将是，
yeah, and the print statement,
是的，打印语句，
actually there's 9,10, sorry 9,11,
实际上这里是 9,10 ，抱歉， 9,11 ，
that's why I got confused,
这就是我困惑的原因，
and the print statement is also going to say,
打印语句也会说，
x was the one that was substract, so 9 11,
x 是减去的那个，所以是 9,11 ，
so we get the string 9,11 out
所以我们得到字符串 9,11 ，
and two value of the accounts are 9,11,
两个账户中的值是 9,11 ，
if two t2 goes first,
如果 t2 先执行，
then the outcome is you know 10,10,
那么结果是 10,10 ，
because nothing no money has moved yet,
因为钱还没有动过，
and then t1 goes,
然后 t1 开始，
so that's a possible outcome.
所以这是一种可能的结果。
And so that's the two legal outcomes of the two transaction,
所以这是两个事务的两种合法的输出，
that we're actually,
我们，
if we executed the two transactions concurrently
如果我们同时执行这两个事务，
and the system guarantees serializability.
系统保证可串行化。
Now you notice that serializability has probably a lot of flavor,
现在你注意到，可串行化有很多特点，
of like the terminology that we used before namely linearizability,
就像我们之前使用的术语线性一致性，
the key difference between serializability and linearizability is that,
可串行化和可线性化之间的关键区别在于，
in linearizability, there's a real-time, a real-time component,
在线性一致性中，有一个实时的组件，
that if transaction t2 start after t1 ends,
如果 t2 在 t1 结束后开始，
then t2 has to show up later in the total order,
那么 t2 必须在整体顺序中出现在后面，
in the serial order,
在串行化顺序中，
in serializability, that is not required,
在可串行化中，那是不需要的，
so even if transaction started
所以，如果事务开始，
were clock time a little bit later than another transaction stopped or finished,
在时间上晚于另一个事务停止或结束，
and the system is still allowed to reorder it,
系统仍然允许对它重新排序，
so serializability in some ways a little bit weaker than linearizability.
所以可串行化在某些方面比可线性化要弱一些。
Nevertheless, serializability is a very convenient programming [idea], right,
尽管如此，可序列化是一个非常方便的编程[思想]，
because from programming perspective,
因为从编程的角度来看，
you could always think about transactions executing in some serial order,
你总是可以考虑事务以某种顺序执行，
and you don't have to consider all kinds of interleavings.
你不必考虑所有的交错。
Okay, so even though serializability slightly weaker than linearizability,
好的，所以即使可串行化略弱于可线性化，
it actually disallows a whole bunch of problematic cases.
它实际上禁止了很多有问题的情况。
So let me talk a little bit about that,
所以让我简单地谈一谈，
just to make clear what actually serializability means,
弄清楚可串行化的含义，
and what sort of executions,
什么类型的执行，
the transactions, the transaction system actually has to forbid?
事务系统必须禁止？
And, so let's, you know two cases,
然后，所以，有两种情况，
like here we have the first transaction,
这里我们有第一个事务，
we have the second transaction running,
我们有第二个事务，
so t1 runs, t2,
所以 t1 运行， t2 ，
and you know one outcome that we could have,
我们可能会有一个结果，
is like one possible execution that might happen is,
一个可能发生的执行是，
if we if we don't do something special,
如果我们不做一些特别的事情，
you know t1 gets x,
t1 get(x) ，
you know here the transfer happens,
这里转账发生，
so the updates x y happen,
所以更新 x,y 发生，
and then you know t2 does get y,
然后 t2 执行 get(y) ，
and you know is this illegal
这是不是非法的，
or is this a serializable, is this a serializable execution?
是不是可串行化的执行？
That's sort of question we have to ask,
这是我们要问的问题，
and what is the answer to that one?
这个问题的答案是什么？
This is not serializable.
这不是可串行化的。
Yeah, and because you know the outcome,
是的，因为你知道结果，
you know if we write down what the outcome is, correct,
如果我们写下结果是什么，
then the outcome is gonna be 9,11 here,
那么结果是，这里是 9,11 ，
and this is going to write down a 10,11, right.
这里是 10,11 。
I think so.
我想是的。
And if we go back to our previous slides,
如果我们回到之前的幻灯片，
that is not one of the two legal outcomes, right,
这不是两个合法结果之一，
so this is not good.
所以这不是好的。
So when we think about the implications of transaction system,
所以，当我们考虑事务系统的含义时，
it has to be the case,
它必须是这样的，
that it forbids this particular execution schedule,
它禁止这种执行安排，
you know this is a simple version,
这是一个简单的版本，
transactions for these two examples are not so complicated,
这两个例子的事务并不复杂，
so there not that many interleavings you have to,
所以不会有太多交错，
you, you could consider that could go wrong.
你认为可能会出问题。
But there's at least one, other one,
但至少还有另外一个，
that can result in not an incorrect outcome,
可能会导致不正确的结果，
which is we do the put x first,
那就是我们先执行 put(x) ，
so here we go,
所以我们开始，
then you know we actually print the two,
然后我们打印两个，
do two gets, get(x) get(y),
执行两个 get ， get(x) get(y) ，
and we do the put(y),
然后我们执行 put(y) ，
is this a serializable execution,
这是可串行化的执行吗，
is this an execution that we should be forbidden by the serializable transaction system,
这是我们应该被可串行化事务系统禁止的执行吗，
or is it okay execution?
还是可行的执行？
It should be forbidden.
这应该被禁止。
It should be forbidden, correct,
它应该被禁止，
because as an outcome,
因为作为结果，
that could not have happened,
不会发生这种情况，
if we executed t1 first followed by t2
如果我们先执行 t1 ，然后执行 t2 ，
or t2 first followed by t1, right.
或者先执行 t2 ，然后执行 t1 。
Okay, so what we clearly see is that,
好的，我们清楚地看到，
you know serializability excludes you know executions,
可串行化排除了（某些）执行，
and just do, in order to actually make it easier for programmers
为了让程序员更容易地
to think about actually what database does.
考虑数据库所做的。
And there are two broad approaches to forbidding executions,
有两种大的方法来禁止执行，
and in these approaches,
而且在这些方法中，
the approach forbidding is called concurrency control.
禁止的方法称为并发控制。
In the first approach,
在第一种方法中，
for the first category of solutions is,
第一类解决方案是，
what is called pessimistic solutions,
所谓的悲观解决方案，
and the pessimistic solution basically involve locks,
悲观的解决方案是引入锁，
so the idea is that,
所以这个想法是，
when the transaction runs or starts,
当事务运行或开始时，
it requires necessary, necessary locks to maintain serializability,
它需要必要的锁来维护可串行化，
and only release the locks when it's guaranteed,
只有确保以下情况才释放锁，
that the executions will result in a serializable execution,
当执行会导致串行化执行时，
so that's one approach
这是一种方法，
and we're going to talk a little bit more about in a second.
我们稍后会更详细地讨论。
The second approach is is is optimistic,
第二种方法是是乐观的，
and in the optimistic approach, there was basically no locks,
在乐观的方法中，没有锁，
and optimistic approach, you just assume things are gonna work out,
乐观的方法，你只是假设一切都会好起来，
and basically when you get to the commit point,
当你到达提交点时，
you know the [] system sort of ask yourself the question,
[]系统问你自己这个问题，
well, you know all the given the operation I've done in the past,
我之前做过的所有操作，
is that actually could that be a the result of a linearizable execution,
这是可线性化执行的结果吗，
or could that be the result of a serializable execution,
或者这是可串行化执行的结果吗，
if so, things are fine, no problem at all,
如果是这样的话，一切都很好，没有问题，
then you know we're good,
然后我们是好的，
if it is result this doesn't correspond to a single execution,
如果结果不对应于单次执行，
they were basically just abort,
它们会被终止，
and maybe and it will retry probably.
它可能会重试。
And so we'll see,
我们将看到，
I'm not gonna talk much about optimistic concurrency control right now,
我现在不会太多地谈论乐观的并发控制，
but next week or two weeks from now,
但下周或两周后，
after reading the FaRM paper,
在读完 FaRM 论文后，
and you'll see an optimistic transaction system, distributed transaction system
你将看到一个乐观的分布式事务系统，
of the type that we're considering,
我们正在考虑的类型，
that uses an optimistic, optimistic control concurrency control approach,
它使用乐观并发控制方法，
but the focus for today is going to be pessimistic.
但是今天的重点是悲观的（方式）。
And one you know sort of the [flip way],
一种[翻转方式]，
that these two approaches are described a in literature often is,
这两种方法在文献中经常被描述为，
sort of pessimistic is,
悲观的（方法）是，
you know you ask for permission first and then you do your operations,
你先获得许可，然后执行操作，
and the optimistic sort the other way around,
而乐观的方式则相反，
you just go ahead and do your operations,
你只管去执行你的操作，
and it turns out to be wrong, you just apologize later.
如果结果是错的，你随后道歉就可以了。
So that is sort of analogy if you will,
所以，如果你愿意的话，这是一种类比，
between the two different approaches.
在这两种不同的方法之间。
And now within each approach,
在每种方法中，
whether it's pessimistic or optimistic,
无论是悲观的还是乐观的，
there are many different concurrency control plans,
有许多不同的并发控制方案，
you know to either increase their concurrency
要么增加它们的并发性，
or provide weaker consistency and with more concurrency,
或者提供更弱的一致性和更多的并发性，
and so there's like a, there's a [huge literature].
所以这是一个[很大的资料]。
And I'm just gonna talk about one particular approach,
我想谈谈一种特殊的方法，
which is very popular,
它非常受欢迎，
particularly if you want to achieve serializability,
尤其是如果你想实现可串行化，
it turns out that not,
事实证明不是，
alrough I said like serializability is a gold standard for databases,
尽管我说过可串行化是数据库的黄金标准，
it's often [] that databases offer multiple degrees of isolation,
数据库提供了多种程度的隔离，
so you know as a programmer,
所以作为一个程序员，
you can sort of pick you know the degree of isolation that you like,
你可以选择你喜欢的隔离度，
and the reason you may want to pick a weaker degree of isolation,
你可能想要选择一个较弱的隔离度，
so that you can get more concurrency.
这样你可以获得更多的并发性。
Now we're going to stick to the gold standard of concurrency,
现在我们将坚持并发的黄金标准，
which is namely serializability,
也就是可串行化，
and if you do serializability,
如果你要实现可串行化，
then a common approache is 2-phase locking,
一种常见的方法是两阶段锁，
in 2-phase locking, basically sort of lock per record,
在两阶段锁中，每个记录都有锁，
that's the starting point for database record,
这是数据库记录的起点，
and you know in our little example,
在我们的例子中，
that would be sort of a lock for variable,
这是对变量的锁，
and lock for x and lock for y.
x 的锁和 y 的锁。
And there's basically two rules,
有两条规则，
one, transaction requires a lock before using,
第一，事务在使用之前需要一个锁，
and so the idea is,
所以这个想法是，
before you know you can read or write you know to x y,
在你可以读写 x y 之前，
you first have to obtain the lock,
你必须先拿到锁，
and the transaction system will do this for you,
事务系统会帮你做到这个，
two, the T holds a lock,
第二， T 持有一把锁，
once you're acquired,
一旦你获取，
you're not allowed to release it until commit or abort,
你不允许释放它，直到提交或中止，
whatever, whatever is the end of the transaction.
无论事务的结果是什么。
Okay, and so in our particular case,
好的，在我们这个案例中，
if we have like T1 running and we have T2 running,
如果我们有 T1 运行， T2 运行，
and T1 locks x first,
T1 首先对 x 加锁，
and then you know lock y,
然后对 y 加锁，
and it has to maintain those locks
它必须维持这些锁，
until it actually reaches commit points,
直到它达到提交点，
so T2 runs at the same time or roughly at the same time,
T2 在同一时间或大致相同时间运行，
if T2 starts a little bit later,
如果 T2 开始得晚一点，
and it tries to grab the lock in x,
它试图获得 x 的锁，
t1 will have it,
T1 拥有它，
if T2 started a little bit later,
如果 T2 开始的时间稍晚一些，
and at that point, basically T2 has to wait,
在这一点上， T2 必须等待，
sort of standard locking protocol.
一种标准的锁定协议。
And the basic idea 2-phase locking is that,
两阶段锁的基本思想是，
it's sort of a refinement or improvement over this simple locking scheme,
它是对这个简单锁方案的改进，
that is described in the document
在文档中描述，
and which sometimes are called simple locking or strict locking,
有时被称为简单锁或严格锁，
where basically at the beginning of the transaction,
在事务开始时，
you grab all of the locks you need for the whole transaction,
你获取整个事务所需的所有锁，
you hold them until the end and then you release them,
你持有它们直到最后，然后释放它们，
and 2-phase locking is a little bit more fine-grained,
而两阶段锁要更细粒度一点，
in that, even if the transactions [],
其中，即使事务[]，
and they are not required to lock immediately
它们不需要直接获取锁，
all at the same time at the beginning,
在开始的时候同时获取所有（锁），
instead, they require the locks incrementally as the transaction runs,
相反，它们在事务运行时以增量方式获取锁，
which allows certain concurrency patterns that are disallowed by strict lock.
允许某些严格锁不允许的并发模式。
Now, the first rule seems pretty clear,
现在，第一条规则似乎很清楚，
why you need it,
为什么你需要它，
the second rule might be, maybe less obvious,
第二条规则也许不那么明显，
and so it's a probably a good idea
这可能是一个好主意，
to actually see what goes wrong,
看看哪里会出问题，
if you did not maintain the second rule.
如果你没有坚持第二条规则。
And so, let's say talk a little bit about until commit,
所以，让我们来讨论一下 until 提交，
and so here we have our two transactions,
所以这里我们有两个事务，
T1 and T2 you know the transfer and the print statement,
T1 和 T2 ，分别是转账和打印语句，
and so let's say you know,
所以我们假设，
here we do our put of x,
在这里，我们执行 put(x) ，
and so that means before the put x,
这意味着在 put(x) 之前，
transaction system locks x,
事务系统锁定 x ，
and let's say that we're not following the 2-phase locking rule,
假设我们没有遵循两阶段锁规定，
and we actually release the lock x right after the put,
我们在 put 之后释放 x 的锁，
because we're done with it,
因为我们已经完成了，
actually doesn't show up in transaction t1 anymore,
不会再出现在事务 T1 中，
there will be a later put, for us put to y,
稍后还有一个 put ， put(y) ，
and let's assume that,
让我们假设，
before actually get to the locking of y, T2 runs,
在获取 y 的锁之前， T2 运行，
and actually T2 basically the whole,
T2 整个是，
you know the two gets, you get of x and get y run,
两个 get ， get(x) get(y) ，你摆脱了x，让y跑了
and so since you know T1 release the lock x,
如果 T1 释放 x 的锁，
you know it can get the lock x,
它可以得到 x 的锁，
since T1 hasn't done to the put yet,
因为 T1 还没有完成 put ，
you know it can also get the lock on y
它也能获得 y 的锁，
and so you know print x and y,
所以打印 x 和 y ，
and reset and then release locks.
然后重新设置，然后释放锁。
So, is this, would this be a serializable execution?
那么，这是一个可串行化的执行吗？
No, it's the same as before.
不，它跟以前一样。
Yeah, exactly the same as before, right,
是的，跟以前一样，
because basically the print statements like here,
因为这里的打印语句，
they sort of slipped in between the two put in x and y,
它们处于两个 put x 和 y 之间，
between the two put of the x and y,
在两个 put x 和 y 之间，
and we already concluded earlier,
我们之前已经总结了，
that is not a serializable conclusion, serializable execution.
这不是可串行化的执行，
So this is wrong,
所以这是错误的，
and so this is a good example of demonstrating,
所以这是一个很好的演示例子，
that if you release the lock too early,
如果你过早地解锁，
in this case T1 release the x too early,
在这种情况下， T1 过早地释放 x ，
you're not gonna get a serializable execution.
你不会得到一个可串行化的执行。
And one way to think about it basically is that,
一种考虑它的方式是，
whatever there's sort of an intersection between you know two lock sets,
在两个锁集中间有交集，
so T1 has a lock set of x and y,
所以 T1 有 x y 的锁集，
T2 has a lock set of x y too,
T2 也有 x y 的锁集，
it is important that,
重要的是，
you know during, these two transactions can order in a particular way,
这两个事务可以以特定方式排序，
that means that if the locks intersect,
这意味着如果锁相交，
you know we have to make ensure some total ordering,
我们必须确保一些整体顺序，
and that means that we actually have to
这意味着我们必须
hold the lock to the end until the commit point,
持有锁直到提交点，
so that no intermediate results of the transaction are actually visible to other transactions,
没有事务的中间结果对其他事务可见，
and we release locks before the commit point,
我们在提交点之前释放锁，
we might actually make a result visible,
我们可能会让结果变得可见，
even though you know may be later it's actually even abort, right,
即使晚点它可能中止，
and then the whole change will go away,
然后，整个变化就会消失，
so this is the reason why the locks must be held to the end.
这就是为什么锁必须持有到底的原因。
Now, an obvious problem that many of you asked about,
现在，你们中的许多人问到的一个明显的问题，
in 2-phase locking,
在两阶段锁中，
is there is a, is there a chance of deadlock,
是不是会有死锁，
if you're requiring the locks as the transactions execute.
如果你在事务执行时获取锁。
And so let's,
所以我们，
this is absolutely the case,
这绝对是一种情况，
and so for example, let's modify T2 slightly,
例如，我们稍微修改一下 T2 ，
so T2 used to be,
所以 T2 原来是，
you know t1 gets x,
t1 get(x) ，
instead we're going to do with in the opposite order refers to get y,
相反，我们要用相反的顺序， get(y) ，
and t2 gets x,
而 t2 get(x) ，
and we remain we keep T1 the same, right,
我们保持 T1 不变，
so T1 actually still the first put to x and then put to y,
所以 T1 仍然是首先 put(x) ，然后 put(y) ，
so now we can easily get into trouble,
所以现在我们很容易陷入麻烦，
so this is T2 prime,
所以这是 T2' ，
and this is just the ordinary T1 that we already have,
这是我们已经有的普通的 T1 ，
it does put of x,
它执行 put(x) ，
you know before doing the put of x
在做 put(x) 之前，
and needs to get the lock on x,
需要获取 x 的锁，
so L locks Lx.
所以锁 Lx 。
Now let's say that the ordering works out as follows,
现在我们假设排序如下所示，
you know the same time to T2' runs,
T2' 同时运行，
it does get y,
它执行 get(y) ，
so that means you've got the lock on y,
这意味着你获得 y 的锁，
and now you can easily see what goes wrong here,
现在你可以很容易地看到这里出了什么问题，
now t1 is gonna do put of y or wants to do put y,
现在 T1 执行 put(y) 或要执行 put(y) ，
so we need to get the lock on y,
所以我们需要获得 y 的锁，
but you can't get it,
但你不能得到它，
because you know T2' actually has the lock,
因为 T2' 已经持有那个锁，
so it has to wait here and the block,
所以它必须在这里等待，并阻塞，
you know same thing is gonna happen of course on the other side,
同样的事情当然也会发生在另一边，
you know when before doing the get of x,
在执行 get(x) 之前，
T2 will need to get the lock of x,
T2 需要获得 x 的锁，
and you know it can't get the lock of x,
它不能获得 x 的锁，
because T1 has it,
因为 T1 持有它，
and so this has to wait too,
所以这个也需要等待，
and now we have you know T1 waiting T2',
现在我们有 T1 等待 T2' ，
and we have T2' waiting T1,
我们有 T2' 等待 T1 ，
we basically have a deadlock.
我们有一个死锁。
Now, what is the cool part about transaction systems is that,
现在，事务系统最酷的部分是，
we have the abort operation,
我们有 abort 操作，
and so if the transaction system could detect a deadlock,
所以，如果事务系统可以检测到死锁，
could use abort one of the two transactions,
可以使用 abort 两个事务中的一个，
let the other one proceed,
让另一个继续，
and hopefully that will actually get to the end and commit
希望它能走到最后并提交，
and abort the other one,
并中止另一个，
and then the client or the application can decide
然后客户端或应用程序可以决定
what to do with abort of transactions,
如何处理事务中止，
it can actually retry it,
它可以重试，
you know may be so wait a little bit and then retry,
可能会稍等片刻，然后重试，
in the hope at that point you're not going to run into a deadlock.
希望在这一点上，你不会陷入死锁。
And so one way to think a little bit about 2-phase locking is that,
所以，考虑一下两阶段锁的一种方式是，
it has a little bit of optimistic you know flavor to it,
它有一点乐观的味道，
in the sense that,
从某种意义上说，
it's not guaranteed,
它没有保证，
it won't run into problems,
它不会遇到问题，
but even if it runs into problems,
但即使它遇到了问题，
you know you can always abort and then recover from that problem.
你总是可以中止，然后从问题中恢复。
Any questions about this?
对于这个，有什么问题吗？
So you say how do you, how do you find the deadlock?
所以你怎么找到死锁？
That's exactly I was hoping that somebody was asking that question.
这正是我希望有人问这个问题。
So the way, there's sort of two broad approaches that people use,
所以，人们使用两种方法，
one is,
一个是，
yeah, one is not solid as well,
也不是可靠的，
one is basically on a timeout basis,
一个是基于超时的，
like if the transaction running for a long time,
比如如果事务运行了很长时间，
and you know they don't seem to make forward progress,
它们似乎没有取得任何进展，
you just abort one of them,
你只是中止其中一个，
and so this timeout based,
所以这个是基于超时的，
the more systematic sort of way of thinking about it is,
一种更系统的思考方式是，
to construct an wait-for graph,
构造一个等待图，
as the transaction systems you know are moving,
随着事务系统的移动，
so for example if t1 runs,
例如，如果 T1 运行，
so a in the wait-for graph,
所以在等待图中，
the transactions are nodes,
事务是节点，
so we got a node T1
所以我们有一个节点 T1 ，
and we make a node T2,
我们创建一个节点 T2 ，
when they start,
当它们开始时，
with T2' if you will,
如果你愿意的话，使用 T2' ，
and when T1 runs you know gets x, [] [],
当 T1 运行 get(x) ，
then gets to the lock of y,
然后获取 y 的锁，
it can't do it,
它不能这样做，
so we'll make an arrow from T1 to T2'
所以我们画一个 T1 到 T2' 的箭头，
to indicate that T1 is waiting for T2',
表示 T1 正在等待 T2' ，
then at some point, like you know T2 running,
然后在某个时候， T2 运行，
you know T2 hits this, T2' hits this point,
T2 到达这个点， T2' 到达这个点，
where it want to lock x, it can't do it.
它想要获得 x 的锁，它做不到。
So we'll look at,
所以我们来看看，
what's waiting for, who's holding the lock,
有什么在等着，谁持有锁，
well, it's t1,
嗯，是 T1 ，
so we'll put an edge you know in the wait-for graph
所以我们在等待图中放一条边，
from T2 to T2' to T1,
从 T2' 到 T1 ，
and now we see there's a cycle,
现在我们看到这是一个环，
and whenever there's a cycle,
当这里出现环时，
that means there's a deadlock,
意味着出现了死锁，
because one is waiting on the other,
因为一个在等待另一个，
and the other is waiting on the first.
而另一个则在等待第一个。
And so, the transaction system can construct these graphs on the fly,
所以，事务系统可以动态构建这些图，
detect when there's a cycle in the graph,
检测图中何时出现环，
and then for example either abort T1 or abort T2'.
然后，例如中止 T1 或 T2' 。
It's call the wait-for graph.
它称为等待图。
What happens after the abort?
中止后会发生什么？
Well, so let's say we have abort T2,
好吧，假设我们已经中止了 T2 ，
just for as an experiment,
只是作为一个实验，
so we're gonna kill this guy,
所以我们要杀死这个，
so T2 basically the transaction system is going to arrange,
所以 T2 ，事务系统将安排，
so we'll see in a second,
我们一会儿就会看到，
it's going to arrange that basically none results of T2
它将安排 T2 没有结果
or t2 is visible,
或者 T2 的结果是可见的，
at that point, the lock is released,
在这一点上，锁被释放，
the abort will force the lock release of the y,
abort 将强制释放 y 的锁，
because t2 is backing out,
因为 T2' 退出，
that means that you know T1 can get the lock on y and proceed to finish,
这意味着 T1 可以获得 y 的锁并继续完成，
the client that called T2' is going to learn,
调用 T2' 的客户端将会知道，
that the transaction abort it,
事务中止了它，
and for general you can just choose to rerun it again.
一般情况，你可以选择重新运行它。
Does it makes sense?
这能理解吗？
Okay, so this is sort of the first part,
好的，这是第一部分，
and you know actually what I wanted to say about 2-phase locking,
我想说的关于两阶段锁，
except I wanted to address the sort of homework assignment again,
另外我想再说一遍家庭作业，
which is like in what situations,
在什么情况下，
does 2-phase locking allow for more concurrency than strict locking,
两阶段锁比严格锁允许更多的并发性，
where strict locking was the protocol,
严格锁是一种协议，
where the transaction acquires all the locks in advance,
事务事先获得全部锁，
and this requires that the programmer
这就要求程序员，
or like the beginning of the transaction basically declares
或者事务的开始声明
which locks the transaction actually needs,
事务需要哪些锁，
sort of slightly indesirable, less programmer friendly,
稍微有点不可取，对程序员不太友好，
but it has the advantage,
但它有一个优势，
that you know you don't actually,
那就是你不需要，
you can run into these,
你可以执行，
you don't have to abort transaction at the end,
你不必在结束时中止事务，
in case you run into a deadlock.
以防你陷入死锁。
So 2-phase locking allow for more concurrency in principle,
所以，两阶段锁原则上允许更多的并发性，
or should allow for more concurrency
或者应该允许更多的并发性
than the strict locking or simple locking scheme.
比严格锁或简单锁方案。
And so I would like to do is a quick breakout room
我想做的是一个快的分组会议室，
for a couple minutes like five minutes again,
过几分钟，比如五分钟，
and you know convince yourself or constructing case,
说服自己或构思案例，
where simple locking which disallows some concurrency,
其中简单锁不允许某些并发性，
that 2-phase locking is actually able to exploit.
而两阶段锁可以使用。
Cool, all right, let's do breakout rooms.
太棒了，好的，我们来进入分组会议室。
Okay, see you in five minutes.
好的，五分钟后见。
We can't hear you.
我们听不到你说话。
I think you're muted.
我想你静音了。
I have a question about one of the previous slides that you're talking about.
我有一个问题，关于你之前提到的一张幻灯片。
Hold on, let me double check if everybody can hear me now.
稍等，我再检查一下现在大家是否都能听到我说话。
Yes.
是的。
Okay, good, go ahead.
好的，很好，继续。
On one of your previous or I guess this is just a general question,
关于你之前的或者我想这是一个一般性的问题，
but is the lock point always the same as the commit point,
但是（释放）锁的点是否总是与提交点相同，
or is it possible to start relinquishing locks before your commit point.
或者，是否可以在提交点之前开始放弃锁。
Okay, this is a very good question,
好的，这是一个非常好的问题，
so depends,
视情况而定，
so if you only do exclusive locking,
所以如果你只执行独占锁，
as we've done so far,
像我们到目前为止所做的，
at least in my examples,
至少在我的例子中，
then commit point is similar to the,
提交点一样，
the lock point is similar to the commit point and the abort point,
（释放）锁的点与提交点和中止点一样，
if you have read write locking,
如果你使用读写锁，
the locks that allow both read locks and write locks,
锁允许读锁和写锁，
then, it's possible to release read locks earlier with some restrictions.
然后，可以在有一些限制的情况下更早地释放读锁。
Okay.
好的。
Okay, so can somebody give me one example
好的，有人能给我举个例子吗，
of where 2-phase locking is allowing for more concurrency than simple locking,
两阶段锁允许比简单锁有更多的并发，
just to make sure we're all on the same page.
只是为了确保我们想法一致。
The audit function example,
比如审计功能，
like you can release the lock as soon as you read this person's amount,
一旦你读到这个人的金额就可以释放锁，
like you don't have to wait until you read everyone's.
你不必读到每个人的。
This is an example of exploiting the read read locks,
这是利用读锁的一个例子，
if you have read locks.
如果你有读锁。
Any other examples?
还有其他例子吗？
If you have a transaction,
如果你有一个事务，
where there's a condition that only rarely like is true,
其中有一个条件很少是 true ，
and you read a piece of data when it's true,
当它是 true 时，你读取一块数据，
so, at the beginning, you don't need to acquire the lock for that,
所以，在开始时，你不需要获取锁，
only when you actually need to read it.
只有当你真的需要读取它时。
Yeah, that's a great example,
是的，这是一个很好的例子，
I personally like that example a lot,
我个人非常喜欢这个例子，
that's a great one.
这是一个很好的例子。
Good, okay, good,
好的，好的，
so let's move on basically down to the second topic of this lecture,
让我们继续这节课的第二个主题，
which is 2-phase commit,
也就是两阶段提交，
this is really dealing with crashes,
这是关于处理崩溃，
switch back to blue and on the white.
换回蓝色，在白板上。
We can't see the slides either yet.
我们还看不到幻灯片。
Oh, let me fix that,
哦，让我来解决这个问题，
and hold on,
稍等，
share screen, step to share,
共享屏幕，开始共享，
how about now?
现在怎么样？
Okay.
好了。
Good, thank you.
好的，谢谢。
Alright, so 2-phase commit or 2PC that's popular called,
好的，所以两阶段提交或通常称为 2PC ，
again this is a very well-known popular protocol,
同样，这是一个非常著名的流行的协议，
I'm going to talk about that,
我将讨论它，
base sort of simple straightforward or the most common version of the protocol,
协议的简单明了或最常见的版本，
they're all kinds of variations of it,
它们是它的各种变体，
but you know in they also have the same underlying idea.
但它们也有相同的基本想法。
And so again, typically in 2-phase protocol,
同样地，通常在两阶段协议中，
and I'm going to do it in the context of the transfer transaction,
我将在转账事务的背景下这样做，
so a client that actually wants to do a transfer,
所以，如果客户端想进行转账，
you know basically submits the transfer transaction to transaction system,
将转账业务提交给事务系统，
and the the machine sort of receive transaction is called the coordinator,
而接收事务的机器称为协调器，
and that machine is in charge of running the transaction through the transaction system,
那个机器负责通过事务系统运行事务，
and so the coordinator will talk in our case to two different machines,
在我们的情况下，协调器将与两台不同的机器交互，
A and B,
A 和 B ，
where A holds you know x and B holds y.
其中 A 持有 x ， B 持有 y 。
And and basically you know one way that this typically goes is that,
而且通常的一种方式是，
the coordinator for a sort of does the whole transaction,
协调者执行整个事务，
but in a tentative way,
但以试探性的方式，
so, the put x you know results in a message to A,
所以， put x 导致一个给 A 的消息，
you know locking A, modifying A,
锁定 A ， 修改 A ，
you know put x, except,
put x ，
the put is not actually visible yet in the database,
put 在数据库中还是不可见的，
what what's done is putting a log,
它所做的是放入一个日志，
very much like in sort of in the Frangipani style,
很像在 Frangipani 中的方式，
where we have to write ahead log,
我们必须预先写入日志，
all the operations,
所有操作，
that we at some point, one of [materialize] in the database itself,
在某个时刻，数据库自己[具体化]，
we first put in the log,
我们首先放入日志，
until later, in the particular case until we hit commit,
在这种情况下，直到我们遇到提交，
and then we actually will install everything in the database.
然后我们将安装数据库中的所有东西。
So we do put, we do second put you know to y,
所以我们执行第二个 put 到 y ，
in another same thing happens there,
同样的事情也发生在那里，
you know we got a lock on y,
我们获得 y 的锁，
okay, so this sort of being lock on x,
好的，这是对 x 的锁，
and we do a put on y,
我们对 y 执行 put ，
and again we're gonna not actually you know really put the value in the database,
再次，我们不会真的把值放入数据库，
we're gonna using log,
我们将是使用日志，
so we're log y
所以我们 log y ，
and here we log x.
这里是 log x 。
Okay?
好的?
And now the coordinator is done two you know the transactions,
现在协调者完成了两个事务，
that two of main operations now so ready to commit,
现在两个操作准备好提交，
and here's where the 2-phase part comes in.
这就是两阶段的用处。
And so the coordinator will send a prepare message,
协调器将发送一个 prepare 消息，
and first gonna describe this protocol,
首先描述这个协议，
indicates there's no failures and everything works out,
表明没有失败，一切都解决了，
you know just sort of the easy cases as will,
是一些简单的案例，
sends a prepare message,
发送一个 prepare 消息，
sends a prepare message to,
发送 prepare 消息到，
to prepare A, you know prepare B,
prepare A ， prepare B ，
and the prepare message of course includes the transaction ID,
并且 prepare 消息当然包括事务 ID ，
that actually used for this transaction,
用于这个事务，
so every transaction has a transaction ID,
所以，每个事务都有一个事务 ID ，
and all the message are tag with the transaction ID,
所有的消息都标记有事务 ID ，
so we always know about which transaction we're talking about,
所以，我们始终知道我们谈论的是哪个事务，
when A and B receives prepare messages,
当 A 和 B 接收到 prepare 消息，
you know they look at their state,
它们查看自己的状态，
you know see if they indeed can actually execute the transaction,
看看它们是否真的可以执行事务，
you know they're holding the lock on x in this case,
在这种情况下，它们持有 x 的锁，
the x is actually the log
x 在日志中，
and so they sent back,
所以它们发回，
you know saying yeah I'm ready to commit,
说是的，我准备好提交了，
So, yes, yes,
所以，是的，是的，
and at this particular point, use the crucial step is,
在这一点上，关键的一步是，
the coordinator now knows that basically both A and B are prepared to commit,
协调者知道 A 和 B 都准备好提交，
and so and I have basically promised to commit by actually responding y,
我承诺要提交，响应 y ，
and at this point the coordinator commits,
在这一点上，协调者提交，
and then you know sends messages you know again to the A,
然后发送消息给 A ，
saying commits you know the transaction TID,
说 commit(TID) ，
similar message to B you know commit TID,
同样的消息给 B ， commit(TID) ，
and at this particular point,
在这一点上，
A and B actually perform the operation,
A 和 B 执行操作，
so they basically install,
所以它们安装，
at this point, you know they install you know the log version of y,
在这一点上，它们安装 y 的日志，
here again, this transaction, this participants installs the x,
同样，这个安装 x ，
and then release the locks,
然后释放锁，
so release y and here the release of x,
所以释放 y ，这里释放 x ，
then they respond back you know to the coordinator,
然后它们回复协调者，
saying like yep all done,
表示所有都完成了，
and at that point, the transaction is completely done,
在这一点上，事务完全完成，
in fact coordinator doesn't really have to
事实上，协调器不需要
remember anything anymore about this particular transaction.
记住有关这个事务的任何内容。
And also see later,
而且，也可以在后面看到，
you know A and B you know need to remember that state a little longer
A 和 B 需要记住这个状态长一点时间，
until they hear about the next transaction.
直到它们听到下一个事务。
Okay, so this is a core basic case,
好的，这是一个核心的基本案例，
when there's absolutely no failures,
当绝对没有失败的时候，
and we see what we actually get the desired outcome, correct,
我们看到我们得到了预期结果，
you know when does the coordinator commits,
什么时候协调者提交，
coordinator commits only if A and B agree.
只有在 A 和 B 同意的情况下，协调者才能提交。
Okay, it could be the case,
好吧，有可能是这样的，
that you know for example when the coordinator sends a message to B,
例如，当协调器向 B 发送消息时，
and B decides, well, I can't really commit,
B 决定，我不能提交，
maybe sort of could be multiple reasons for it,
可能有多种原因造成这种情况，
maybe the B actually is in a situation,
也许 B 处于一种情况，
where there's a deadlock with y,
y 有一个死锁，
or you know there's no space in the log anymore,
或者日志已经没有空间，
or there's not enough money in the account of y
或者账户里没有足够的钱，
and, and so you know B could respond with an no,
所以 B 可以回复不，
let's say in this,
假设在这里，
so the other possible outcome is
另一个可能的结果是，
you know the prepare message can actually send a no back,
prepare 消息可以发回一个 no ，
and in that case,
在这种情况下，协调员得到A的肯定，B的否定，
the coordinator gets one yes you know from A, a no from B,
协调者得到一个来自 A 的 yes ，一个来自 B 的 no ，
and so both do not agree,
所以双方都不同意，
and in that case,
在这种情况下，
you know the coordinator cannot commit the transaction,
协调者不能提交事务，
and then it would actually abort the transaction,
然后它可以中止事务，
and then sends the abort messages to A and B,
然后向 A 和 B 发送 abort 消息，
basically discontinuing the transaction,
停止事务，
so those are the two possible outcomes,
所以这是两种可能的结果，
one is the commit case, one is the abort case,
一个是提交的情况，一个是中止的情况，
and when it is always the case,
它总是这种情况，
that the transaction only commits,
事务仅提交，
the top level transaction only commits,
顶层事务仅提交，
both the participants that are involved in the transaction agreed to do so.
当参与事务的双方都同意这样做。
Now, that's sort of the outline of the protocols,
现在，这就是协议的概述，
I want to now go through a couple of cases
现在我想看几种情况，
you know sort of to understand you know what can go wrong,
理解什么会出错，
and how we do, how we deal,
我们如何处理，
how 2-phase commit arranges that actually still the right thing happens.
两阶段提交如何安排仍然是正确的。
Actually I have a question, yeah.
我有个问题。
So we said that, like B might decide that it needs to abort,
所以我们说， B 可能会决定它需要中止，
sends back no message,
发回 no 消息，
what if it decides it needs to abort after it replied yes,
如果它在回复 yes 之后，决定需要中止，
would that ever be possible?
这有可能吗？
No, we'll talk about in a second,
不，我们一会儿再谈，
but that's absolutely not possible,
但这绝对是不可能的，
if you promise to commit, you have to commit.
如果你承诺提交，你必须提交。
Or you have to be ready to commit.
或者你必须做好提交的准备。
You have to be ready to commit,
你必须准备好提交，
you don't commit right away,
你不立即提交，
you have to wait until the commit message of course,
必须等到提交消息，
but you can not [] out anyone,
但你不能[反悔]，
so until the prepare,
所以，直到 prepare ，
the B can unilaterally abort the transaction,
B 可以单方面中止事务，
once promise yes,
一旦承诺 yes ，
it cannot unilaterally abort the transaction anymore.
它不能再单方面中止事务。
So, is it possible where you in deadlock,
所以，有没有可能你陷入死锁，
but you can't get out of the deadlock,
但你无法摆脱死锁，
because everyone in that cycle has agreed to prepare commit.
因为环中的每个都同意准备好提交。
If everybody agrees to prepare,
如果每个人都同意准备，
they can definitely commit, then they will commit,
它们肯定会提交，它们就会提交，
and you're still holding locks.
你仍然持有锁。
Right, but what if you're in a deadlock,
是的，但如果你陷入死锁，
because we mentioned before,
因为我们前面提到了，
one of the reasons why you might want to abort.
你可能想要中止的原因之一。
You would find it out before to prepare,
你会在准备好之前发现它，
if you get the locks of y,
如果你得到了 y 的锁，
if you did not succeed in getting those necessary locks for the transaction,
如果你没有成功获得事务所需的锁，
then you know at that point.
那么你在那个点上就知道了。
Right, thank you.
好的，谢谢。
Okay, so this is exactly the kind of discussion is going to come up,
好的，这就是将要进行的讨论，
I'm gonna, I'm gonna take the same board and replicate it,
我将使用同样的白板，并复制它，
and consider a bunch of different cases,
考虑一系列不同的情况，
so here's the same board again,
所以这是相同的白板，
nothing has changed so far, it's identical,
目前为止什么都没有改变，它是一样的，
and so let's the first to sort of
所以我们首先，
follow up on this question that we're just ask,
跟进我们刚才提出的这个问题，
let's first consider the case where B is in the prepared state,
让我们首先考虑 B 处于准备状态的情况，
and then crashes right after,
然后崩溃了，
so it is prepared,
所以它是准备好的，
it pointed back, send back to coordinator,
它发回给协调者，
that actually is agreeing to go along,
同意一起去做，
and then right after it sends actually the prepare message ok message,
然后在它发送 prepare 消息 ok 消息后，
it actually crashes,
它崩溃了，
what does that mean,
这是什么意思，
what needs to happen,
我们需要做什么，
how we're going to resolve this,
我们如何解决这一问题，
or what is the risk,
或者风险是什么，
so basically if B crashes.
如果 B 崩溃。
If B crashes, we need to abort the whole thing, right.
如果 B 崩溃，我们需要中止所有东西。
Now, we cannot abort anymore, right,
现在，我们不能中止了，
because you know B already promised,
因为 B 已经承诺了，
that is going to commit.
它将会提交。
We're going to use the log?
我们要使用日志吗？
Yeah, well, okay, so B is gonna crash,
是的，好的，所以 B 要崩溃了，
at some point is going to come back up, right,
在某个时刻，会重新出现，对吧，
it's going to recover hopefully.
希望它会恢复。
And what state does need to remember across crashes?
哪些状态需要记住，在崩溃过程中？
A needs to remember that prepared.
A 需要记住是准备好的。
Yeah, and need to remember correct,
是的，还需要记住，
that it prepared for transaction ID, whatever the TID was,
它准备好的事务 ID ，无论 TID 是什么，
and that is holding the lock on y.
以及持有 y 的锁。
And so when it comes back up,
所以，当它恢复时，
the first thing it has to do sort of look, saying like how,
它首先要做的是查看，
was I in the middle of a participant in a distributed transaction,
我是否在分布式事务的一个参与者中间，
and if you look at the state,
如果查看状态，
and you'll see that,
你将看到，
it was actually prepared for transaction ID, TID,
它为事务 ID TID 准备好了，
and it was and it must hold the lock for Ly,
它也必须持有锁 Ly ，
but the lock for y before it does anything else,
获得 y 的锁在做任何其他事情之前，
you know before talking to anything,
在于其他交互之前，
once it is in that state,
一旦它处于这种状态，
then it as if it didn't crash, right,
就像它没有崩溃，
and things are back to normal,
所有东西都回归正常了，
and hopefully at some point the coordinated will retry the commit message,
并且希望在某一时刻协调者将重试 commit 消息，
the B will get up commit message for this transaction ID,
B 将获得该事务 ID 的 commit 消息，
sees that, yeah I'm indeed prepared,
看到我确实准备好了，
and I hope the lock at y,
我希望 y 的锁，
and so it goes along and installs y and etc,
所以，它继续并安装 y ，等等，
finishes the transaction.
完成这个事务。
Is that makes sense?
这能理解吗？
So basically you know there's a little bit of refinement here,
所以这里有一些改进的地方，
that we actually have to write some stable you know data to stable storage,
我们必须将一些数据写入到稳定存储中，
you know as part of the transaction,
作为事务的一部分，
and which was part of 2-phase commit,
这是两阶段提交的一部分，
this is one of the reasons the 2-phase commit is a little bit expensive,
这是两阶段提交有些昂贵的原因之一，
because not only we have to send sort of multiple round messages,
因为我们不仅要发送多个回合的信息，
but also participant actually has to write things to stable storage,
而且参与者必须将东西写到稳定存储中，
and as we've talked about before,
正如我们之前讨论过的，
writing to stable storage, it's quite expensive, right,
写入稳定存储是昂贵的，
like could be easily a couple milliseconds,
可能很容易就是几毫秒，
you know let's say one millisecond optimistically,
让我们乐观地说一毫秒，
that means basically,
这意味着，
that were immediately limited to a thousand transaction per second,
直接被限制在每秒 1000 个事务，
no more.
不会更多。
Okay, let's consider another case,
好的，让我们来考虑另一个情况，
and so let me duplicate this slide again,
所以让我再复制一次这张幻灯片，
and consider yet another case.
考虑另一种情况。
Let's say, we the coordinator crashes,
比如，协调者崩溃，
and so you know here's red again, which pencil,
所以，这里使用红色铅笔，
and you know we got like one, we got prepared messages,
我们有一个，我们有准备好的消息，
and the coordinator maybe you know send one commit message,
协调者可能已经发送了一条 commit 消息，
and then crashes right here,
然后在这里崩溃，
you know what, what do we need to arrange
我们需要安排什么，
to make sure that the whole plan works out.
确保整个方案顺利实施。
So the coordinator needs to store in a persistent storage what are what are the commands,
所以协调器需要将命令持久化存储，
that were promised to be committed, but we're not committed yet.
已经承诺提交，但还没有提交的。
Yeah, so the coordinator is almost the same as analysis, analysts to B's case, correct,
是的，所以协调者几乎和对 B 的分析相同，
if we commit a transaction,
如果我们提交一个事务，
we need to write to stable storage,
我们需要写入稳定存储，
that we're actually committing the transaction,
我们正在提交事务，
so we need to write to stable storage you know commit TID,
因此我们需要写入稳定存储， commit tid ，
so that when the coordinator comes back up,
这样当协调者回来的时候，
then it can actually finish the transaction
然后它才能完成事务，
until actually the A and B indeed transaction is committed,
在 A 和 B 事务提交之前，
because A and B are waiting, right,
因为 A 和 B 都在等着，
A and B says, like yeah we're happy to go along,
A 和 B 说，是的，我们很乐意继续，
and they're waiting waiting
它们一直在等待，
until actually they hear from the coordinator to decide what's done,
直到它们听到协调者决定完成，
because once they decided, once they went along,
因为一旦它们决定，一旦它们继续，
once they agreed to go along,
一旦它们同意继续，
you know they cannot unilaterally anymore [], correct,
它们就不能单方面[]，
because, let's say they actually both said that they agreed at all,
因为，假设它们都说完全同意，
then it means that the coordinator
那就意味着协调者，
and they don't know they made,
它们不知道，
the coordinator send a commit message to for example A
协调者发送 commit 信息给 A ，
and actually has commit transaction,
表示提交事务，
B hasn't heard yet,
B 还没有收到，
maybe the message got delayed, then the coordinator got crash,
可能消息延迟了，然后协调者崩溃了，
and you know that point,
在这一点上，
it would be totally wrong for B to abort the transaction,
B 中止事务将是完全错误的，
it really has to wait until the coordinator comes back
它必须要等到协调者回来，
to tell what actually the outcome is of the transaction.
判断事务的结果是什么。
Okay?
好的?
So only,
所以，只有，
sorry, the only message that the coordinator is not going to resend is prepare,
抱歉，协调者不会重新发送的唯一消息是 prepare ，
that one if it gets, like doesn't get a yes, it'll just abort?
如果它没有得到 yes ，它就会中止？
Yeah, it was the next example, so let's do that.
是的，这是下一个例子，所以我们继续。
Let me duplicate this board again,
让我再复制一下这个白板，
and talk about that case.
然后谈谈这种情况。
So, just for [], let's move it down,
所以，为了[]，我们把它移到下面，
so [],
所以[]，
let's say you know following thing happens,
假设下面的事情发生，
the this prepare message never makes it, right,
这个 prepare 消息永远不会出现，
and then you know the coordinator can unilaterally decide to abort, right,
然后协调者可以单方面决定中止，
and in fact you can tell B you know to abort,
事实上，你可以告诉 B 中止，
and A doesn't really need to know anything about it [],
A 不需要知道任何关于它的事情，
the someone later you know will come up and ask the coordinator,
有些会晚点回来问协调者，
the coordinator doesn't know anything about any more about this transaction,
协调者不知道关于这个事务的任何更多信息，
you can just tell A, that transaction is actually abort,
你可以告诉 A ，那个事务已经中止，
because I don't have a commit record anymore,
因为我没有提交记录，
I was not waiting to inform anybody.
我没有等待通知任何人。
So in that case, we can do an abort,
所以在这种情况下，我们可以中止，
and that means that B can release the locks, correct
这意味着 B 可以释放锁，
and B can just proceed,
B 可以继续，
you know happily trying to the other transactions that might involve y.
尝试其他可能涉及 y 的事务。
Okay?
好的?
Sorry, so what will happen if the message to A gets lost,
抱歉，如果给 A 的信息丢失会发生什么，
the coordinator aborts,
协调器中止，
and then B crashes,
然后 B 崩溃了，
but then when it comes up
但是当它回来时，
is going to wait for commit message from coordinator,
它将等待来自协调者的提交消息，
but the transaction has aborted already.
但这个事务已经中止。
Yeah, or yeah so either these two cases,
是的，这两种情况，
you know presumably you know the most protocols actually B will ping the coordinator,
大多数协议 B 会 ping 协调者，
because it knows who's the coordinator,
因为它知道谁是协调者，
and ask what's the outcome of that transaction.
并询问这个事务的结果是什么。
Okay, so one more case, I want to return to one case,
好的，我想再谈一种情况，
there's actually sort of the most interesting case,
有一种最有趣的情况，
one of the more tricky cases.
是最棘手的情况之一。
So I just have a brief question.
所以我有一个简单的问题。
Yeah, hold on one second.
好的，等一下。
Sorry.
抱歉。
Yeah.
好的。
Yeah, so the first question is that,
好的，所以第一个问题是，
so let's B let's say holds the lock on y,
假设 B 持有 y 的锁，
all the way through between putting y into the log,
直到把 y 放入日志，
and so installing y to [].
把 y 安装到[]。
Yes.
是的。
Okay.
好的。
And then the second question,
然后是第二个问题，
so the locks here are distributed,
这里的锁是分布式的，
because we are dealing with across servers,
因为我们在处理跨服务器的问题，
or I mean if y only exist on the server B,
我的意思是，如果 y 只存在于服务器 B 上，
then maybe we don't need this to be locking,
或许我们不需要对它加锁，
I'm just curious of what the setup.
我只是好奇是怎么回事。
Yeah, the setup is here basically,
是的，这里的设置，
that A maintains the lock for all the shards that it has,
A 维护它的所有分片的锁，
for all the variables, all the records that it has,
它的所有的变量，所有的记录，
B maintained the lock for all the records it has.
B 维护它所有的记录。
Okay, but if we,
好的，但如果我们，
for example have y being on multiple servers,
例如， y 在多个服务器上，
then we need some sort of distributed lock?
那么我们需要某种分布式锁？
Yeah, like we were talking about the sharded case, right,
是的，我们在谈论分片的情况，
where the accounts are sharded across multiple servers,
帐户分片在多个服务器之上，
and only one server has a particular account.
只有一台服务器有特定的帐户。
Awesome, thank you.
太棒了，谢谢。
I'm Come back to this later, actually one more time.
我稍后再回到这个问题上，再说一次。
So the first thing I wanted to point out is,
所以我想指出的第一件事是，
just go back to sort of the, the case,
回来看看这种情况，
where B or A you know said yes and then crashes, correct,
B 或 A 回复 yes ，然后崩溃了，
or actually yeah, let me see if that's the case,
或者，让我看看是不是这样，
no, I want the case of following case, right,
不，我想下面这种情况，
fix this line,
修复这条线，
so A and B promised their thing,
所以 A 和 B 承诺了，
but I want to go back to the case,
但我想回到这个情况，
where that we already discussed,
我们已经讨论过了，
which is right after the commit point,
也就是在提交点之后，
the coordinator crashes.
协调者崩溃。
Okay.
好的。
And, and we know correct this interval of time from here to there,
而且，我们知道这段时间，从这里到那里，
basically B cannot unilaterally abort anymore, right,
B 不能再单方面中止了，
because it promised to go along,
因为它承诺会继续，
and it might have been the case,
也有可能是这样的，
that actually A did actually already did commit,
A 已经提交了，
and so it cannot unilaterally abort anymore,
所以，它不能再单方面中止了，
and so there's only one option in this case,
所以在这种情况下只有一个选择，
what is that one option?
是哪种选择？
We just wait.
我们只能等待。
Yeah, it's unfortunate but true,
是的，这很不幸，但却是真的，
the only thing that we can do is wait,
我们唯一能做的就是等待，
and it's still holding the lock on y, correct,
它仍然持有 y 的锁，
so that means that,
所以这意味着，
any other transaction that involves y you know cannot proceed,
任何其他涉及 y 的事务都不能继续进行，
one has to wait you know until the coordinator comes back,
必须等待协调者回来，
and announces or re-announces whatever decision was,
宣布或重新宣布决定，
that actually was the outcome for that particular transaction.
那个事务的结果是什么。
This is one of the sort of the two aspects,
这是两个方面中的一个，
you know this one of these aspects of 2-phase commit,
这是两阶段提交的其中一个方面，
that are been desirable, right,
这些都是可取的，
where the protocol might just block until a machine comes back.
在那里协议可能会被阻塞，直到机器回来。
Does that make sense?
这能理解吗？
So how do people deal with this in practice,
那么，人们在实践中是如何处理这一问题的，
well, it's a little bit unfortunate,
好吧，这有点不幸，
but the here's were some of our techniques from the past can come to rescue,
但这里是我们过去的一些技巧可以来拯救，
you know what could we do with the coordinator,
我们能对协调者做些什么，
to make this scenario unlikely.
让这种情况变得不太可能。
So we can make it fault tolerant, like.
我们可以让它容错。
Yeah, make fault tolerant, how could we do it?
是的，做容错，我们怎么做呢？
Well, there are multiple approaches, but,
好的，有多种方法，但是，
you can do it maybe through raft.
你可以通过 raft 来做这件事。
Yeah, you know run raft
是的，运行 raft
to basically basically run the coordinator not on a single machine,
使协调者不是在一台机器上运行，
we basically have a replicated state machine that implements the coordinator,
我们有一个复制状态机来实现协调者，
and you know we use raft
我们使用 raft
to sort of keep the replicated state machine
来保持复制的状态机
and implement the coordinator in sync,
实现协调者同步，
and then if one of the machines that forms the coordinator fails,
然后，如果组成协调器的机器中的一台发生故障，
hopefully the two others are still there,
希望另外两个还在那里，
and so we can still proceed, right,
所以我们仍然可以继续，
and so it's potentially possible to basically
所以有可能，
you know replicate the coordinator
复制协调者，
or actually any of the participants to you know using raft.
或者任何参与者使用 raft 。
So let me actually,
所以让我，
so discuss this a little bit and talk a little bit more,
所以让我来讨论一下，
a couple of discussion points,
有几个讨论点，
which is you know we could use Raft
我们可以使用 Raft ，
to make a coordinator fault tolerant or available, if you will,
使协调器容错或可用，
it's really property we care about.
这是我们关心的性质。
Does that make sense?
这能理解吗？
In fact, you will see,
事实上，你会发现，
if you do lab 4 instead of a project,
如果你做的是实验 4 而不是一个项目，
this is exactly what lab 4 does,
这正是实验 4 要做的事情，
lab 4 actually has a similar scheme,
实验 4 实际上也有类似的方案，
where there's a form of 2-phase commit,
有一种形式的两阶段提交，
that you implement and move the the master shard or the master coordinator,
你实现，移动 master 分片或 master 协调者，
and then rebalances shards across shard servers,
然后在分片服务器之间重新平衡，
uses Raft replicated to actually replicate itself,
使用 Raft 复制，
to shard servers itself, also replicated itself using Raft,
分片服务器也使用 Raft 复制，
and so where many, many Raft groups running in parallel,
所以，许多 Raft 组并行运行，
and also the essence of lab 4,
也是实验 4 的实质所在，
and so this is like typically way,
所以这就是通常的方式，
you know if you're concerned about
如果你担心，
having the system being blocked for a long period of time,
系统长时间阻塞，
one way to do it is
一种方法是，
basically make the coordinator fault tolerance.
使协调者容错。
So that [] brings me to something else,
所以[]让我想到了另一件事，
which a lot of people ask about,
很多人问到，
you know is Raft, are Raft and 2-phase commits sort of similar things,
Raft 和两阶段提交是不是类似的东西，
or could you do 2-phase commit with raft
或者你可以使用 Raft 做两阶段提交，
or you need to have a little bit of a parallel, correct,
或者你需要有一些并行，
like one thing is called coordinator, raft called the leader,
比如，一个东西叫做协调者， Raft 叫做领导者，
we gotta participants, you know maybe we can figure out these as followers,
我们有参与者，也许我们可以把这些当作跟随者，
so you know seems to have some similarities,
所以似乎有一些相似之处，
like how do we think about it,
我们怎么考虑它，
what's the relationship between Raft and 2PC?
Raft 和 2PC 之间有什么关系？
The difference is that,
不同之处在于，
in Raft the coordinator can change essentially,
在 Raft 中，协调者可以改变，
otherwise it's like the single point of failure.
否则，它就是单点故障。
Yep, good point, any?
是的，很好的观点，还有其他的吗？
So another difference is that,
另一个不同之处是，
the Raft basically depends on the concept of a majority,
Raft 是基于多数的概念，
whereas in 2-phase commit coordinator,
而在两阶段提交协调者中，
it needs to get a response from every single other server,
它需要从每个其他服务器获得响应，
that is involved in the.
所有涉及到的。
Yeah, good point,
是的，很好的观点，
so these are almost like critical differences, right,
所以这些几乎就是关键的区别，
and you know we're wondering if we get to a point,
我们在想，如果我们到了一个点，
where like if there's a conceptual difference,
比如，如果概念上的差异，
like do they solve the same problem?
它们是否解决了相同的问题？
Oh, Raft is for replicating the same thing,
哦， Raft 是用来复制相同的东西，
and 2-phase commit, when you do the opposite,
两阶段提交是相反的，
when you instead of having one thing you spread across different servers,
不是让一个东西传播到不同服务器上，
then you have to deal with the problem.
那你就得处理这个问题。
Exactly, in Raft, all servers do the same thing,
没错，在 Raft 中，所有服务器都做同样的事情，
implementing replicate state machine, right,
实现复制状态机，
and in 2PC, actually servers were all servers operate on different data,
而在 2PC 中，所有服务器操作不同的数据，
the first participant was actually operating on x,
第一个参与者在 x 上操作，
and second participate was operating on y,
第二个参与者在 y 上操作，
so in 2PC, really you know solve a completely different problem than Raft,
所以在 2PC 中，解决了一个与 Raft 完全不同的问题，
Raft is really all about high availability,
Raft 是关于高可用性，
and 2PC is really about atomic operations across servers,
2PC 是关于跨服务器的原子操作，
across data that's living on different servers.
跨位于不同服务器上的数据。
Does that make sense?
这能理解吗？
So even though like maybe they have some internal techniques that look very similar,
所以，即使它们可能有一些内部技术看起来非常相似，
the two protocols you knwo are designed for completely different problems,
这两个协议是为完全不同的问题而设计的，
and not directly related,
没有直接的关系，
now it's interesting to see, correct,
现在看起来很有趣，
but we could make Raft,
但我们可以做 Raft ，
we can use Raft to make the coordinator more fault tolerant,
我们可以使用 Raft 使协调者具有更强的容错性，
or participants made more highly available,
或者参与者更高的可用性，
but they basically essentially solve different problems.
但它们本质上解决了不同的问题。
With that, I actually wanted to end this lecture,
说到这里，我想结束这节课，
I'm happy to entertain more questions,
我很乐意回答更多的问题，
hopefully this will very helpful in the next two papers,
希望这对接下来的两篇论文有帮助，
so the next two papers are both two transaction systems,
所以接下来的两篇论文都是两个事务系统，
one and one from Google,
一个来自 Google ，
one from Microsoft research,
一个来自微软的研究，
and second one uses optimistic transactions,
第二个使用乐观事务，
and you'll see when you read these papers,
当你读到这些论文的时候，你会发现，
there's a lot of machinery, are pretty complex systems,
有很多机制，都是相当复杂的系统，
but hopefully at least some of the parts that will be described,
但有希望的是，至少有一部分将被描述，
you will now understand,
你现在就会明白，
because you know what 2-phase commit is
因为你知道什么是两阶段提交，
and you know what two-phase locking is.
而且你知道什么是两阶段锁。
Okay, with that, I'll end,
好的，说到这里，我就结束了，
and everybody needs to go can go,
每个需要离开的认就可以离开，
and anybody wants to ask questions,
如果有人想问问题，
you know please feel free to do so.
请自由提问。
Sorry, this might be a little, a strange question,
抱歉，这个问题可能有点奇怪，
but for 2-phase locking,
但对于两阶段锁来说，
it is also about atomic operations,
它也是关于原子操作的，
but there it is about one, not across servers, but across one server,
它是关于，不是跨服务器，而是在一台服务器，
and 2-phase across multiple servers.
两阶段是跨服务器的。
Yeah, 2-phase locking is relevant too, if you have a single machine,
是的，如果你只有一台机器，两阶段锁也是有关的，
like a multi-core machine,
比如一台多核机器，
and you're implementing a transaction system on a multi-core machine,
你在一台多核机器上实现事务系统，
you will have to lock you know the records that are involved in the transaction,
你必须对事务中涉及的记录加锁，
and 2-phase locking is a perfectly good protocol for doing so,
对于这个，两阶段锁也是一个非常好的协议，
where 2-phase commit is really about the distributed systems.
而两阶段提交真正是关于分布式系统的。
I guess my question was is 2-phase 2-phase locking,
我想我的问题是，两阶段锁，
can it be part of 2-phase commit?
它可能是两阶段提交的一部分吗？
I'm not sure I know what that means,
我不确定那是什么意思，
the way I think about is that,
我的想法是，
you solve two different problems.
你解决两个不同的问题。
Okay.
好的。
It's the case that,
事实是，
you know you you maybe this is what you mean,
也许这就是你的意思，
it is a case where that you know there's a coordinator,
在这种情况下，有一个协调者，
or as part of the initial setup,
或者作为初始设置的一部分，
when the initial puts are done by the transaction,
当初始 put 通过事务完成时，
the that transaction will follow 2-phase locking,
这个事务遵循两阶段锁，
here to lock on x required, to lock on B required,
这里需要获取 x 的锁，需要获取 B 的锁，
so the lock y is required,
需要获取 y 的锁，
and so does the transaction does that in the 2-phase locking style,
事务做这个是使用两阶段锁的方式，
it could have done using strict locking too,
它也可以使用严格锁，
but you know from the 2-phase commit point of view,
但是从两阶段提交的角度来看，
it doesn't really matter,
这不重要，
at some point, you know the transaction is [] to be executed
在某一点上，事务将要执行，
and the 2-phase commit is really about reaching agreement,
两阶段提交是为了达成协议，
that all parties agreed to go along.
所有各方都同意继续。
Yeah, that makes sense, thank you.
好的，理解了，谢谢。
You're welcome.
不用谢。
Is 2-phase commit exclusively for like sharded data?
两阶段提交是专门用于分片数据吗？
No, actually it came out,
不，事实上它来自，
well, oh, yes or no,
好吧，是或不是，
the original sort of 2-phase commit came out of the case,
最初的两阶段提交来自这种情况，
where like you have different organizations,
比如你有不同的机构，
and they need to agree to do something,
它们需要同意做一些事情，
like you know you book on a travel website,
比如你在旅游网站上预定，
you know you book a trip,
你预定一趟旅行，
and another thing you book a hotel,
还有一件事，你订了酒店，
and you want to commit to the whole trip,
你想提交整个旅行，
if you both hotel website and the travel website agreed to go along,
如果酒店网站和旅游网站都同意，
sort of committed to the transaction
那么提交这个事务，
and that sort of deciding where sort of this deciding where,
这决定，
came up which really you know you have different organizations,
来自不同的机构，
they need to commit to a particular operation,
它们需要提交一个特定的操作，
and for the reasons that,
出于这样的原因，
that that setting actually basically people don't really want to use 2-phase commit,
人们并不想使用两阶段提交，
because that would mean that,
因为这就意味着，
the travel agency website is dependent on the hotel reservation websites,
旅行社网站依赖于酒店预订网站，
and these are from different organizations,
它们来自不同的机构，
and you know people who know the organization don't really trust each other,
机构并不彼此信任，
and if one goes down,
如果其中一个停机了，
then there's actually can't proceed and that seems all bad,
然后就不能继续了，这看起来很糟糕，
so, in fact, 2-phase commit have a bit of a negative reputation,
所以，两阶段提交有点负面名声，
because really you know,
因为你知道，
one of the original goals of 2-phase commit to solve that problem,
两阶段提交的最初目标之一是解决这个问题，
that problem here, people don't really want to solve with 2-phase commit,
这里的问题，人们不希望使用两阶段提交来解决，
however in the context where you have a data center,
然而，在拥有数据中心的环境中，
it's a single organization and the databases sharded,
是一个单一的机构，数据库是分片的，
2-phase commit is widely popular and typical use.
两阶段提交是广泛流行和典型使用。
Awesome, thank you.
太棒了，谢谢。
You're welcome.
不用谢。
Could you go back to the first failure case,
你能回到第一个失败的情况吗，
that we talked about with 2-phase commit,
我们谈到的两阶段提交，
where it fails, B fails after responding prepare ok.
B 在回复 prepare ok 之后崩溃，
Yeah, is this one?
好的，是这个吗？
Yeah, I guess.
是的，我想是的。
I talked twice about this case, but like.
关于这个情况我谈了两次，但是。
Yeah, I guess I was wondering,
是的，我想我想知道，
why B needs to persist
为什么 B 需要持久化，
or like why needs to remember that it received prepare,
或者为什么需要记住它收到了 prepare ，
I guess my thinking was,
我想我的想法是，
when it comes back up,
当它恢复时，
if it receives A commit message from the coordinator,
如果它从协调者接收到 commit 消息，
couldn't it just assumed that it was prepared,
它就不能假设它已经准备好了吗，
I guess where does it use that information.
我想它在哪里使用那个信息。
Yeah, well, it could have abort right before the crash,
是的，它可能在崩溃前中止，
and B needs to remember what it did.
B 需要记住它做了什么。
Okay.
好的。
So there's another slight variation with this protocol,
这个方案还有另一个细微的变化，
where where you assume that you always commit,
当你假设你总是提交，
so presume commit one of the messages slightly different,
假设提交，其中一条消息略有不同，
and you know there's an optimization that you could consider,
你可以考虑一个优化方案，
and would make sense in some settings,
在某些情况下也是有意义的，
I I didn't really talk about that particular protocol,
我并没有真的谈到那个特定的协议，
but just a slight different,
但只是略有不同，
you know sort of variation,
一种变体，
there's quite a number of variations for 2-phase commit,
两阶段提交有相当多的变体，
they change in minor ways.
它们会有一些微小的变化。
Make sense?
理解了吗?
Yep, thank you.
是的，谢谢。
Is that it for today?
今天就这些吗？
Sorry, you said that it can,
抱歉，你说它可以，
it could have aborted the transaction,
它可以中止事务，
but if it did, that it will never receive the commit.
但如果它这样做，它将永远不会收到提交。
You mean in response to the last question?
你的意思是回应最后一个问题？
Yeah.
是的。
You know the the question was,
这个问题是，
like why does B have to record on stable storage,
为什么 B 必须记录到稳定存储，
what decided to do.
决定要做什么。
And the injury is that when B comes up,
问题是，当 B 出现时，
it knows it needs to know whether actually commit, agreed to commit,
它需要知道是否同意提交，
or going to agree to abort,
或者同意中止，
and it doesn't write anything, it doesn't know to what agree.
它没有写任何东西，它不知道同意什么。
Because it could have been abort, after.
因为它可能中止，之后。
Yep.
是的。
Yeah.
好的。
I need to know that,
我需要知道，
you know what to do in the recovery stage, I see.
在恢复阶段做什么。
Yes, exactly.
是的，没错。
It also needs to record what it does,
它还需要记录它所做的事情，
because if it like aborts,
因为如果它中止，
but the message never gets to the coordinator,
但消息永远不会到达协调者，
needs to resend the same message, right.
需要重新发送相同的消息。
Yeah, well, it need to record that actually abort that transaction ID,
是的，它需要记录中止那个事务 ID ，
so when the coordinator asks you know what did you do,
所以当协调者问起你做了什么，
that actually responds with a no.
它回复一个 no 。
Got it, thank you.
明白了，谢谢。
Thank you.
谢谢。
You're welcome.
不用谢。
Alright, see you all next week.
好的，下周见。